The Black Lizard...
黒蜥蜴
本字幕由诸神字幕组出品，仅供学习交流，禁止用于商业用途
The Armed Detective Agency
武装探偵社はポートマフィアの武闘派「黒蜥蜴」の襲撃を受けた
was attacked by the Port Mafia's
military squad, the Black Lizard.
更多中日双语字幕，尽在 www.kamigami.org 和微博 @诸神字幕组
But Kunikida-san, Yosano-san, and Kenji-kun
しかし　その一団を
诸神微信公众号正式上线啦，搜索「诸神字幕组」添加关注吧
国木田さん達はあっという間に撃退してしまった
humiliated the entire team with ease.
Such is the might of the Armed Detective Agency.
武装探偵社恐るべしだ
Hey, hey, Harunocchi.
ねぇねぇ春野っち
Can you take the marble out of this bottle?
この瓶の中からビー玉取り出してくれる？
Sure, right away.
はい　ただいま
A marble?
ビー玉？
Is this what you wanted, Rampo-san?
これでよろしいですか　乱歩さん
Yes.
いいよね　ビー玉
Marbles are nice, aren't they?
いいですよね　ビー玉
Yes, marbles are nice.
Um, isn't Rampo-san going to help?
あの　乱歩さんは手伝わないんですか
Kunikida-kun.
国木田君
I need to head off to a job soon.
僕　そろそろ名探偵の仕事に行かないと
ああ　殺人事件の応援ですね
Oh, to help with the murder case?
全く　この街の警察は僕なしじゃ犯人一人捕らえられないんだからな
Indeed, the police in this city can't even nab a single criminal without my help.
Still,
でも　まあ…
my Ultra Deduction is the best
ability in this agency,
僕の「超推理」はこの探偵社　いや…
or even the whole nation.
この国でも最高の異能力だ
I guess it's no wonder
that everyone depends on it.
みんなが頼っちゃうのも仕方ないよね
We're indebted to you, Rampo-san.
頼りにしてます　乱歩さん
判ってればよろしい
Good, as long as you're aware.
そう　君らは探偵社を名乗っておいて
That's right.
Though you call yourselves
a detective agency,
その実　猿ほどの推理力もありゃしない
you all can't deduce better than a single monkey.
この探偵社が探偵社であるのはみんな　僕の異能力「超推理」のおかげだよ
The only reason you can call yourselves
a detective agency and function as one
is because of my ability, Ultra Deduction.
Ultra Deduction is so amazing.
凄いですよね　「超推理」
An ability that lets you see right to
the heart of any case instantly.
使うと事件の真相が瞬時に判っちゃう能力なんて
探偵社　いえ　全能力者の理想です
You're a role model for the Agency,
no, for all gifted people.
当然だね
Of course.
Brat.
小僧
はっ　はい
Y-Yes?
Never mind the mess here.
ここの片付けはいいから　乱歩さんにお供しろ
Go with Rampo-san.
The place is close by train.
現場は列車ですぐだ
M-Me as a detective's assistant?
ぼ…僕が探偵助手ですか
そんな責任重大な…
That's a great responsibility.
Of course not.
まさか
I'm not some two-bit detective.
二流探偵じゃあるまいし　助手なんて要らないよ
I don't need an assistant.
じゃあ　僕は何を
Then why am I going with you?
Well, see, I don't know
how to travel by train.
ほら　僕…
列車の乗り方判んないから
そ
の
重
い
足
を
膝
前
へ
導
く
sono omoi ashi o hiza o mae ni michibiku
That feeling pulls your feet onward,
その重い足を膝を前へ導く
负
责
人
Maki
负责人
chikara nanda tte Go ahead to
Telling you to go ahead towards a new power.
力
は
何
だ
っ
て
Go
ahead
問
う
力は何だって Go ahead 問う
kimi no naka ni shoujiru shoudou wa Treasure
That impulse born within you is a treasure!
君
の
中
に
生
じ
る
衝
動
は
treasure
君の中に生じる衝動はtreasure
honmon ka nisemono ka tsureteike yo
Whether it's real or fake, just take it along!
日
听
小
伍
长
田
Cris
翻
译
兰
樱
Naga
校
对
小
伍
江
本
物
か
偽
物
か
つ
れ
て
行
け
よ
日听
小伍
长田Cris
翻译
兰樱
Naga
校对
小伍
小江
本物か偽物か つれて行けよ
kuusou no kanata notte boku no mata mo taemai yo
Straddling the limits of this fantasy, my legs probably won't last,
空
想
の
彼
方
ま
で
僕
の
中
怠
慢
よ
空想の彼方まで 僕の中の怠慢よ
soredemo ii yo yume demo
But that's just fine, even if it's only a dream.
时
间
轴
阿
水
压
制
Coolkid
さ
ら
っ
て
も
い
よ
夢
で
も
时间轴
阿水
压制
Coolkid
さらってもいいよ 夢でも
todokisou de todokanai Make some noise
It seems within reach, but somehow too far off, so make some noise!
届
き
そ
う
で
届
か
な
い
make
some
noise
届きそうで届かない make some noise
kuukyo na nichijou wa kagayakidasu noka
Are these empty days gonna start shining bright?
空
虚
な
日
常
は
輝
き
出
す
の
か
空虚な日常は輝き出すのか
吐
き
出
す
よ
う
に
し
て
前
に
漕
げ
ば
hakidasu you ni shite mae ni mae ni kogeba
If we push on through like we're about to hurl,
吐き出すようにして前に前に漕げば
bokura no mirai wa kasoku shiteyuku darou
I'm sure our future will start to pick up speed!
僕
ら
の
未
来
は
加
速
し
て
い
く
だ
ろ
う
僕らの未来は加速していくだろう
今
こ
の
時
が
止
ま
る
と
し
て
も
ima kono toki ga tomaru to shitemo kono kokyuu made
Even if this moment in time becomes frozen,
今この時が止まるとしても
こ
の
呼
吸
ま
で
止
め
ら
れ
は
し
な
い
さ
この呼吸まで止められはしないさ
tomerare wa shinai sa kudaranai gohoubi mada?
There's no stopping this breath, so where's my worthless reward?
く
だ
ら
な
い
くだらない
ご
褒
美
ま
だ
？
ご褒美まだ？
Wow.
Honestly, I was surprised.
正直　驚いた
He knew absolutely nothing,
切符の買い方　改札の通り方　ホームの場所
including how to buy a ticket,
how to get through the turnstile,
本当に何にも判んないとは
or how to find which
platform to go to.
I guess he really can't do anything
without his ability.
異能力を使わないと　この人何にもできないんだな
You're late, agents.
遅いぞ　探偵社
Oh, who are you?
あれ　君誰
Where is Yasui-san?
安井さんは？
I'm Minoura.
俺は箕浦　安井の後任だ
I took over for Yasui.
This case has been reassigned
to our division.
本件はうちの課が仕切ることんなった
So we no longer need you or your agency.
拠って　貴様と探偵社はもう不要だ
How foolish.
莫迦だなあ
この世の難事件は須く名探偵の仕切りに決まってるだろう
All difficult cases in the world should obviously be overseen by a great detective.
We won't need a
detective today.
今日は探偵になど頼らない
殺されたのは俺の部下だからな
Because the victim is my subordinate.
A lady.
ご婦人か
She was discovered floating in the river this morning.
今朝　川を流されているところを発見されました
She was shot three times in the chest.
胸部を銃で三発
We don't know where or when she was killed.
殺害現場も時刻も不明
We haven't even found the bullets.
弾丸すら発見できない
Any suspects?
犯人の目星は？
No.
判らん
As far as anyone at the office knew,
職場での様を見ていた限りでは　特定の交際相手もいなかったようだ
she wasn't in a relationship, either.
Does that mean you have no leads?
それってさ
何も判ってないって云わない？
Which is exactly why
だからこそ　素人あがりの探偵などに任せられん
we can't let some amateur private eye handle this.
おーい
Hey!
The net caught something!
網に何か掛かったぞ
What's that?
何です　あれ
We've strung a net across the river
to catch any evidence.
証拠が流れていないか川に網を張って調べているのですが
It's a man!
人だ　人が掛かってるぞ
There's a man in the net!
なにっ
What?!
Could there be a second victim?
まさか第二の被害者？
Hey there, Atsushi-kun.
やあ　敦君　これは奇遇だね
What a strange coincidence.
A-Another drowning attempt?
ま…また入水自殺ですか
What, committing suicide alone?
いや　独りで自殺なんてもう古いよ　敦君
That's so passé, Atsushi-kun.
私は確信した
I have come to realize
that if I shall die,
I must die with a beautiful lady!
矢張り死ぬなら美人との心中に限る
ああ　心中　この甘美な響き
Ah, double suicide.
What a sweet ring it has.
それに比べ　独りこの世を去る淋しさのなんと虚しいことだろう
In comparison,
it feels so empty to bid this world
farewell all by my lonesome.
So,
というわけで　一緒に心中してくれる美女をただいま募集中
I'm currently on the lookout for a
beautiful woman who'll die with me!
Huh?
じゃあ　今日のこれは？
Then what was all this about?
I was simply drifting along the river!
これは単に…
川を流れてただけ
I see.
なるほど
By the way, Atsushi-kun,
ところで敦君　こんな処で何してるの
what are you doing out here?
仕事ですけど
I'm on a job.
A job?
仕事？
What kind?
何の
Wh-Wh-Wh-What a tragedy.
ななな…なんてことだ
What a great tragedy this is,
かくの如き佳麗なるご婦人が若き命を散らすとは
that a young beautiful woman in
her prime has lost her life.
悲嘆でこの胸が破れそうだよ
Sorrow is crushing my heart!
She may as well have committed
double suicide with me!
どうせなら私と心中してくれればよかったのに
Who the hell is he?
誰なんだ　あいつは
A colleague at the Agency.
探偵社の同僚で　まぁ　ああいう男だ
That's just how he is.
しかし安心したまえ　ご麗人
But rest in peace, milady.
稀代の名探偵が必ずや君の無念を晴らすだろう
An extraordinarily amazing
detective will avenge you.
Right, Rampo-san?
ねぇ　乱歩さん
ところが　僕は未だに依頼を受けてはいないのだ
But I have yet to get the job itself.
What?
どういうことです
Why?
Ask this man.
この人に聞いて
We have no need for detectives.
探偵などに用はない
In fact, all of my subordinates are far
superior to any private detective.
実際俺の部下は全員　私立探偵などより余程優秀だ
Oh?
What's your name?
君　名前は？
What?
I am Sergeant Sugimoto.
自分は杉本巡査であります
殺されたこの山際女史の後輩であります
The victim, Ms. Yamagiwa,
was my senior!
All right, Sugimoto-kun.
よしっ　杉本君
Solve this case in sixty
seconds, starting now.
今から６０秒でこの事件を解決しなさい
60 Seconds
What?!
I can solve it in under a minute.
僕なら一分以内に解決できる
僕より優秀だと豪語するなら　できるよねぇ
If you're as good as he says you are,
you should be able to do the same.
Okay, give it a try, Sugimoto-kun!
それでは杉本君　云ってみよう
What?!
Um, okay, well...
えーとえーと　いくら何でも６０秒ってのは
Sixty seconds is a bit
overkill, isn't it?!
はい　あと５０秒
Okay, fifty seconds left.
What?!
This is what I must look like.
普段の僕はきっとこんな感じなんだろうな
Oh, right.
あっ　そうだ
最近山際先輩は政治家の汚職疑惑とポートマフィアの活動を追ってました
Yamagiwa-senpai was pursuing
a political corruption case
and also investigating the Port Mafia.
I believe the murderer's M.O. is similar to
the Mafia's method of exacting retribution.
確かマフィアの報復の手口に似た殺し方があった筈です
Maybe she was killed by the mafia
members she was investigating—
もしかすると　先輩は捜査していたマフィアに殺されて…
違うよ
Incorrect.
What?
The Port Mafia's retaliatory methods are as
highly specific as a government-issued ID.
ポートマフィアの報復の手口は身分証と同じで
細部まで厳密に決められている
First, the traitor is forced
to bite the curb,
先ず裏切り者に敷石を噛ませ
後頭部を蹴り　顎を破壊
then they kick the back of
their head to shatter the jaw.
激痛に悶える犠牲者をひっくり返し
As their victim writhes in agony,
they flip him over,
then shoot them in the chest three times.
胸に三発
If we're being specific, yes, but...
確かに…正確にはそうですが
So this M.O. is similar to the
Mafia's, but not the same.
この手口はマフィアに似ているが　マフィアじゃない
That means...
つまり
An attempt at a cover-up?
犯人の偽装工作？
Shooting two extra rounds
into the body just for that?
偽装の為だけに　遺骸に二発も撃つなんて
How cruel.
非道い
Beep!
Okay, time's up!
はい　時間切れ
駄目だね　名探偵の僕には矢張り遠く及ばない
Too bad, you've got a ways to
go before you reach my level.
At the very least, this proved
that your subordinates
少なくとも　君の部下が全員僕より優秀というのは間違っていると証明されたねぇ
aren't all superior to me.
いい加減にしろ
Cut the crap!
You've been going on and on about
deduction and great detectives.
先刻から聞いていれば　やれ推理だのやれ名探偵だの
通俗創作の読み過ぎだ
You've been reading too much pulp fiction!
Cases are solved by thorough investigations,
事件の解明は即ち　地道な調査　聞き込み　現場検証だろう
interviewing persons of interest,
and analyzing the scene of the crime.
Huh?
まだ判ってないの
When are you going to realize it?
名探偵は調査なんかしないの
Great detectives don't do "investigations."
僕の能力「超推理」は
My ability, Ultra Deduction,
can instantly identify the killer
ひと目見れば犯人が誰で　いつどうやって殺したか瞬時に判るんだよ
and when and how the murder was committed.
のみならず
Furthermore,
I can see in my mind's eye how
I can make the killer confess,
どこに証拠があって　どう押せば犯人が自白するかも啓示の如く頭に浮かぶ
and where the evidence lies,
as if it's an epiphany.
I am gifted, after all.
僕は異能力者だからね
Given my line of work,
職業から異能力者の存在は俺も知っている
I know about the gifted's existence.
だがそんな便利な異能力があるなら　俺達刑事は要らねぇじゃねぇか
But if you have such a convenient ability,
why do my colleagues and I still have a job?
まさにその通り
Right on!
漸く理解が追いついたじゃないか
You've finally caught up.
You bastard!
貴様ァ
まぁまぁ　刑事さん
Now, now, Detective.
Rampo-san's always like this.
乱歩さんは終始こんな感じですから
Motto:
All's well
that's well for me!
Motto:
All's well
that's well for me!
After all, my motto is,
何しろ僕の座右の銘は…
Motto:
All's well
that's well for me!
Motto:
All's well
that's well for me!
Motto:
All's well
that's well for me!
Motto:
All's well
that's well for me!
Motto:
All's well
that's well for me!
Motto:
All's well
that's well for me!
Motto:
All's well
that's well for me!
Motto:
All's well
that's well for me!
Motto:
All's well
that's well for me!
Motto:
All's well
that's well for me!
Motto:
All's well
that's well for me!
Motto:
All's well
that's well for me!
Motto:
All's well
that's well for me!
Motto:
All's well
that's well for me!
Motto:
All's well
that's well for me!
Motto:
All's well
that's well for me!
Motto:
All's well
that's well for me!
Motto:
All's well
that's well for me!
Motto:
All's well
that's well for me!
Motto:
All's well
that's well for me!
"All's well that's well for me!"
「僕が良ければすべてよし！」だからな
Motto:
What's better
than being alive?
Motto:
What's better
than being alive?
I've never heard a more convincing motto in my life.
座右の銘を聞いて　こんなに納得したのは初めてだ
Motto:
What's better
than being alive?
Motto:
What's better
than being alive?
Motto:
What's better
than being alive?
Motto:
What's better
than being alive?
Motto:
What's better
than being alive?
Motto:
What's better
than being alive?
Motto:
What's better
than being alive?
Motto:
What's better
than being alive?
Motto:
What's better
than being alive?
Motto:
What's better
than being alive?
Motto:
What's better
than being alive?
Motto:
What's better
than being alive?
Motto:
What's better
than being alive?
Motto:
What's better
than being alive?
Motto:
What's better
than being alive?
Motto:
What's better
than being alive?
Motto:
What's better
than being alive?
Motto:
What's better
than being alive?
Motto:
What's better
than being alive?
Motto:
What's better
than being alive?
Motto:
Have a pure, cheerful,
and energetic suicide.
Motto:
Have a pure, cheerful,
and energetic suicide.
Well, well.
Motto:
Have a pure, cheerful,
and energetic suicide.
Motto:
Have a pure, cheerful,
and energetic suicide.
Motto:
Have a pure, cheerful,
and energetic suicide.
Motto:
Have a pure, cheerful,
and energetic suicide.
やれやれ
Motto:
Have a pure, cheerful,
and energetic suicide.
Motto:
Have a pure, cheerful,
and energetic suicide.
Motto:
Have a pure, cheerful,
and energetic suicide.
Motto:
Have a pure, cheerful,
and energetic suicide.
Motto:
Have a pure, cheerful,
and energetic suicide.
Motto:
Have a pure, cheerful,
and energetic suicide.
Motto:
Have a pure, cheerful,
and energetic suicide.
Motto:
Have a pure, cheerful,
and energetic suicide.
Motto:
Have a pure, cheerful,
and energetic suicide.
Motto:
Have a pure, cheerful,
and energetic suicide.
Motto:
Have a pure, cheerful,
and energetic suicide.
Motto:
Have a pure, cheerful,
and energetic suicide.
Motto:
Have a pure, cheerful,
and energetic suicide.
Motto:
Have a pure, cheerful,
and energetic suicide.
Since you praise it so much,
let's see this ability of yours.
そこまで云うなら見せてもらおうか　その能力
おや　それは依頼かな
Oh?
Are you asking if I can handle the case?
You should've just asked me from the start.
最初から素直に頼めばいいのに
Heh, you have a lot of confidence
about this difficult case
何の手掛かりもないこの難事件を相手に大した自信じゃないか
despite the lack of any evidence.
Want me to count to sixty?
６０秒計ってやろうか
I don't need that long.
そんなに要らない
Watch closely, Atsushi-kun.
よく見ていたまえ　敦君
This is the ability that
keeps the Agency going.
これが探偵社を支える能力だ
Once he puts on those glasses,
あの眼鏡を掛けると　乱歩さんは「超推理」のスイッチが入る
Rampo-san's Ultra Deduction is active.
Rampo-san's ability reveals
the truth about a case.
事件の真相が判る能力　本当にそんな力が存在するのか
Does such a gift really exist?
異能力
Ability: Ultra Deduction!
「超推理」
I see.
なるほど
"I see," my ass.
何が「なるほど」だ
You're trying to imply you
know who the killer is?
犯人が判ったとでも云うのか
Of course.
勿論
Huh?
The killer
犯人は…
is you.
君だ
That's right.
そう　犯人は
The killer...
The killer is you,
犯人は君だ
Sergeant Sugimoto.
杉本巡査
What?
Rampo-san?
乱歩さん？
Sergeant Sugimoto is my subordinate.
杉本巡査は俺の部下だぞ
杉本巡査が彼女を殺した
Sergeant Sugimoto is the one who killed her.
Don't be stupid!
莫迦云え
大体こんな近くに都合よく犯人がいるなど
It's impossible that the killer would appear nearby in the first place!
犯人だからこそ　捜査現場にいたがる
It's because he's the killer
that he wants to stay close to the case.
Besides, didn't I mention this?
それに云わなかったっけ？
I also know where the evidence lies.
どこに証拠があるかも判るって
Lend me your gun, will you?
拳銃貸して
Y-You've got to be kidding.
ば…莫迦云わないでください
The punishment for handing a government-issued
firearm to a civilian
一般人に官給の拳銃を渡したら　減俸じゃ済みませんよ
is far worse than a pay cut.
And here I was hoping you'd have a point.
何を云い出すかと思えば
探偵って奴は口先だけの阿呆なのか
Are you detectives just talk?
その銃を調べて何も出てこなければ　確かに僕は
If we examine that gun and come up empty,
then sure, I'm just a dumbass running my mouth.
「口先だけの阿呆」ってことになる
I've had enough of listening to you!
貴様の口舌三寸はもう沢山だ
Show him, Sugimoto!
杉本　見せてやれ
But...
ですが…
ここまで吠えたんだ
He's dug himself a deep hole,
納得すれば大人しく帰るだろう
If we disprove him,
he'll shut up and go home.
We can't waste any more time.
これ以上時間を無駄にするわけにはいかん
Show him your gun!
こいつに銃を見せてやれ
Hey, what's the matter, Sugimoto?
おい　どうした　杉本
Even in this city,
いくらこの街でも　素人が銃弾を補充するのは容易じゃあない
it's not easy for an amateur
to get spare ammo.
even harder if the firearm
was government-issued.
官給品の銃であれば尚更だ
Why aren't you saying anything, Sugimoto?!
何を黙ってる　杉本
He's thinking hard right now
彼は今懸命に考えている最中だよ
使ってしまった三発分の銃弾について
about the three bullets he used,
and how he'll explain their absence.
どう言い訳するかをね
Sugimoto!
杉本
You can't be the killer!
お前が犯人の筈がない　早く銃を見せろ
Show us your gun, now!
That's right, Sugimoto.
そうだ　杉本
Not good.
まずい
Sugimoto!
杉本
敦君　行け
Atsushi-kun!
Go!
止めろっ
Stop!
Let me go!
放せ　僕は関係ない
I have nothing to do with this!
Running away won't help.
逃げても無駄だよ
The murder took place
early yesterday morning
犯行時刻は昨日の早朝
at the abandoned shipyard,
140 meters upstream from here.
場所はここから１４０メートル上流の造船所跡地
How'd you know that?
何故それを
そこに行けばある筈だ
If we go there, we should be able to
find yours and the victim's footprints,
君と被害者の足跡
それに　消しきれなかった血痕も
as well as the bloodstains you
couldn't fully clean.
How?
どうして…　バレる筈ないのに
No one could've known.
Let's hear the rest back at the station.
続きは職場で聞こう
It may be the last time it's
your place of work.
お前にとっては
最後の職場になるかもしれんが
I didn't intend to shoot her.
撃つ心算はなかったんです
She...
彼女はある政治家の汚職事件を追っていました
She was going after a certain
politician for corruption.
What they didn't predict
そこで予想外にも　大物議員の犯罪を示す証拠品を入手したんです
was that she actually found evidence
of a major Diet member's crime.
However, the Diet member was savvy
しかし議員も老獪で　警察内のスパイを使って
and tried to use a mole inside the police
to get rid of the evidence.
その証拠を消そうとしました
And you're that spy.
そのスパイが君というわけだね
I'd always wanted to
become a police officer.
昔から警察官に憧れていました
After I failed the exam three times, I was depressed.
試験に三度落ちて　落ち込んでいる時に男に声をかけられたんです
That was when a man reached out to me,
どうしても警察官になりたいかと
asking me if I was willing to
do anything to become a cop.
After joining the police force
with the Diet member's help,
そして議員の力で警察官になった僕は
I had to follow his orders in return.
見返りに指示に従っていました
So you killed Yamagiwa as one of his dogs!?
それでお前は議員の狗として山際を殺したのか
That's not it!
違います
I was trying to warn her.
自分は彼女に警告を…
I told her she'd get herself killed
if she didn't give up the evidence.
このままでは消されるから　証拠を手放せと
But she...
しかし彼女は…
Yamagiwa-san, he's taking
this very seriously.
山際さん　相手は本気です
ならばこちらも本気になるだけよ
Then I'll just have to take
him very seriously, too.
I've already made contact
with a prosecutor I know.
馴染みの検察に渡りはつけたわ
後は証拠を渡すだけ
I just need to hand over the evidence.
Sugimoto-kun?
杉本君？
証拠品を渡してください
Please hand over the evidence.
If I fail in this,
もし僕が証拠の奪取に失敗したら　次は殺し屋が動く
he'll call a hit man.
Just stop here.
その前に
Hand over the gun, Sugimoto-kun.
銃を下ろしなさい　杉本君
You can't shoot me.
あなたに私は撃てない
That's right.
その通りだ
That's why
だから　脅し方を変える
I have another way to force you.
Don't!
やめなさい　杉本君
Sugimoto-kun!
If you did nothing,
you'd be convicted
このままでは殺人犯
You'd be fired from your job.
警察も馘首になる
In a panic, you could only think of one
person to go to for help. How ironic.
混乱した君の頼れる人物は　皮肉なことに　一人しかいなかった
When you called the Diet member,
電話した君に議員は証拠隠滅の方法を教えて
he told you how to destroy the evidence.
Just as you were told to, you fired
two more shots into her chest
君はその通りに　彼女の胸にもう二発撃ち　マフィアの仕業に偽装
to make it seem like the Mafia had done it.
You set her adrift in the
river to delay discovery.
発見を遅らせる為　川に遺体を流した
Where is the evidence Yamagiwa obtained?
山際が入手した証拠品はどこだ
That Diet member's responsible
for Yamagiwa's death!
その議員は山際の仇だ
Tell me, Sugimoto!
云え　杉本
Hey, Sugimoto-kun.
ねえ　杉本君
Want me to guess what her
final words to you were?
彼女の最後の言葉　中ててみようか
It was "I'm sorry." wasn't it?
「ごめんなさい」だね
I'm... sorry.
ごめん…なさい
You really
本当に
see through everything, don't you.
凡てお見通しなんですね
The evidence is in my desk drawer.
証拠品は僕の机の抽斗にあります
Thanks, I guess.
世話んなったな
Also, I'm sorry I doubted your capabilities.
それに　実力を疑って悪かった
If we run into another problematic case, we'll ask for your help.
難事件に当たったら　また頼む
If you need my abilities,
僕の力が必要になったら　いつでもご用命を
ask me any time.
I'll give you a discount next time.
次からは割引価格でいいよ
That'd be helpful.
そいつは助かる
Rampo-san was amazing.
凄かったですね　乱歩さん
I had no idea he'd figure everything out.
まさか全部中てちゃうなんて
His ability, Ultra Deduction, is amazing.
異能力「超推理」本当に凄いです
I might've figured out half of it, too.
私も半分くらいは判ったかなー
何がです
Half of what?
だから先刻の事件だよ
About that case just now.
About how Rampo-san figured it out.
乱歩さんがどうやって推理したか
Oh, but he said his ability lets
him figure it out instantly.
だってそれは異能力に拠って瞬時に判るって
That's right, you don't know yet.
君はまだ知らなかったか
Actually, Rampo-san isn't gifted.
実はね　乱歩さんは異能力者じゃないのだよ
Huh?!
はい？
Rampo-san is a very rare
ungifted civilian at the agency.
乱歩さんは異能力者揃いの探偵社では珍しい
何の能力も所持しない一般人なんだ
He himself seems to believe
he's using an ability, but...
本人は異能力を使ってる心算みたいだけどね
Oh, and despite his appearance,
he's 26 years old.
それにああ見えて乱歩さんは二十六歳だよ
What?
The reason why everyone at the
Agency respects Rampo-san
探偵社の皆が乱歩さんを敬うのは
is because they know his
Ultra Deduction isn't an ability.
「超推理」が異能力じゃないと知っているからさ
I'd heard of it, myself,
私も話には聞いていたけど　今日はっきりと思い知らされた
but I only witnessed its
power first-hand today.
To tell you the truth,
実は私ね
while he was "using" his
Ultra Deduction ability today,
乱歩さんが「超推理」をしている間
後ろでこっそりと乱歩さんの髪の毛を摘まんでいたのだよ
I was secretly pinching his hair behind him.
As you well know,
知っての通り　私は触れた相手の異能力発動を阻害する反異能力者だ
I can neutralize anyone's ability if
I touch them. I'm anti-gifted.
No gifted can ever use their ability
while I'm touching any part of them,
私が体の一部に触れている限り
如何なる超人異能力者といえども　力を振るうことはできない
no matter how strong their powers may be.
In other words,
つまり
his Ultra Deduction is not an ability.
乱歩さんの「超推理」は異能力じゃない
It's not?
異能力じゃない？
じゃあ…どうやって
Then how'd he...
It's just deduction, pure and simple.
だからあれは　純粋に推理だ
But how?
そんな…
だって　あんな短い時間で犯人を中てたんですよ
He figured out who the killer was
in such a short amount of time!
Is mere deduction enough to
make such a thing possible?
そんなことがただの推理で可能ですか
Right.
I could tell too, actually.
それなら私にも判ったよ
Remember what Sergeant Sugimoto said?
あの杉本巡査云ってたよね
Shooting two extra rounds
into the body, just for that?
偽装の為だけに　遺骸に二発も撃つなんて
Anyone who saw a body
with three gunshot wounds
Illustration
でも　三発撃たれてる死体を見たら
would assume they were fired at the same time.
誰だって　三発同時に撃たれたって思うよ
Oh.
つまり彼は一発目で被害者が死んだことを知っていたのだよ
In other words,
he knew that the victim had
perished from the first shot.
How could he have known
that before an autopsy?
解剖がまだなのに　それを知っているってのは？
Only if he was the killer.
犯人だけ
But he also knew when it happened,
でも　犯行時間も中てましたよね　「昨日の早朝」だって
early yesterday morning.
That's because the body was
still in good condition.
それはね
遺体の損壊は少なかったから　川を流れたのは長くて一日
So, at most, it'd only been
floating in the river for a day.
Yesterday was Tuesday, a weekday.
昨日は火曜　平日だ
But the victim wasn't wearing any makeup.
なのに遺体は化粧もしていなかった
A detective working long hours,
often late into the night,
激務で残業の多い刑事さんが平日に化粧なしとくれば
would only be like that on a weekday
死んだのは早朝
if the murder had occurred
in the early morning.
I see.
そうか
But how did he know the crime scene,
他の犯行現場とか銃で脅したとかはどうやって？
and that she was threatened with a gun?
That, I don't know.
そこまではお手上げだよ
Rampo-san probably caught a lot
more details than I could hope to.
乱歩さんの目は私なんかよりずっと多くの手掛かりを捉えているだろうし
That's true.
そうですよね　彼女の最後の言葉まで中てちゃうくらいだから
He even guessed her final words.
Oh, that.
あれはね
She supposedly wasn't seeing anyone,
彼女に交際相手はいないって話だったよね
but her wristwatch was an
overseas brand-name item.
でも彼女の腕時計は海外の銘柄物だった
It's not something a single woman
would buy for herself.
独り身の女性が自分用に買う品じゃあない
And Sergeant Sugimoto's watch was the
men's version of the same model.
それと杉本巡査の腕時計も同じ機種の紳士用だった
Then they were...
じゃあ…あの二人は
She went to meet him early when he called,
早朝の呼び出しに化粧もせずに駆けつける　そして
without bothering to put on makeup.
And their watches are of the same model.
同じ機種の腕時計
They were dating.
二人は恋人同士だったのだよ
That's why he couldn't curbstomp her,
だから彼は彼女の顔を蹴って砕くことができなかったんだ
even though he knew it wouldn't
look like the Mafia's work.
そうしないと　マフィアの仕業に見せかけられないとは判っていても
The ability to see through all that
それを見抜く能力も　それが異能力ならば　それは現象だ
would be par for the course if it
were an actual ability.
Nothing more, nothing less.
それ以上でもそれ以下でもない
But if it's due to his personal powers
of deduction, that's a different story.
だが　本人の推理力であるとすれば話は別だ
He's solved dozens of cases in the past.
乱歩さんが過去に解決した事件は十や二十ではない
In every case,
それら凡ての事件において
一見しただけの僅かな情報から真相を一瞬で見抜き
he was able to instantly determine the truth
of the matter with the slimmest of leads.
そして　ただの一度も推理を外さなかったことになる
He's never been wrong, either.
What a great man.
実に偉大なご仁だね
Hey, guide!
ほら　案内係
I can't find my way back to the
Agency on my own, you know!
僕一人じゃ探偵社に帰れないでしょうが
I think I kind of get it now.
なんとなく判りました
Why everyone at the Agency
trusts Rampo-san so much.
探偵社のみんなが乱歩さんを信頼してる理由が
僕が良ければ全て良し
All's well that's well for me!
boku ga boku de irareru
I was searching for the reason
僕が僕でいられる　理由を探していた
riyuu o sagashiteita
why I'm able to stay as I am.
anata no mune no naka de
If there's a version of me
あなたの胸の中で　生きている僕がいるのならば
ikiteiru boku ga iru no naraba
that exists in your heart,
kurayami mo nagai sakamichi mo
Then even if darkness looms on this rocky road,
暗闇も長い坂道も　越えて行けるような僕になれるはず
koeteikeru you na boku ni nareru hazu
I'll be able to find the way to the new me.
sorezore ni ima o aruiteru bokura ga waraeru you ni
So that we can keep smiling in our own moments,
それぞれに今を歩いてる僕らが笑えるように
ikiteiru imi o tashikameainagara susumeru you ni
So that we can explore the meaning of life together,
生きている意味を確かめ合いながら進めるように
namae o yobu yo anata no namae o
I'll call out a name, your name.
名前を呼ぶよ　あなたの名前を
anata ga anata de ireru you ni
So that you can stay how you are.
あなたがあなたでいれるように
kanashimi ni kurete anata no namida ga koboreru toki
Whenever you're overcome by grief, and tears flow,
悲しみに暮れてあなたの涙がこぼれる時
samishisa ni afureta kokoro ga shibondeku toki
Whenever your heart floods with loneliness and you waste away,
寂しさに溢れて心がしぼんでく時
namae o yobu yo anata no namae o
I'll call out a name, your name.
名前を呼ぶよ　あなたの名前を
僕の名前を呼んでくれたみたいに
boku no namae o yondekureta mitai ni
Just as you once called out mine.
What is the Ideal?
理想とは何か
There are any number of
answers to that question.
その問いへの答えは無数にある
曰く言葉である
It is words,
思想である
it is thought.
五年後の引越し計画から夕食の献立に至るまで
From a move scheduled
five years from now
to tonight's dinner menu,
実に細々と人生計画の凡てを書いてあるこの手帳は
this notebook has everything in life
written out in exacting detail.
俺の理想の凡てだ
It represents the entirety of my ideals!
でも　理想の女性図を書いたその頁だけは
But you should never show anyone
the page where you've written about
the ideal woman.
本当誰にも見せないほうがいいですよ
次回　「文豪ストレイドッグス」第六話
Next time on Bungou Stray Dogs, Episode 6:
The Azure Messenger.
Episode 6
The Azure Messenger
「蒼の使徒」
女性に理想を求めて何が悪い
What's so bad about looking
for an ideal woman?!